# 今天我兄弟说带我上山摘野果
Today my brother will take me to pick some wild fruits in the mountains
# 我们要走多久啊
How long does it take to walk there?
# 要走一个小时
One hour
# 一个小时？ #大写表达震惊
ONE HOUR?
# 锻炼身体嘛
Just do some exercise
# 你确定是一个小时
One hour, seriously?
# 这条山路不好走
It's difficult to make our way into the mountains
# 好累啊 嘿嘿嘿
Sounds tiring. [Laughters]
# 没事啊 等下我背你回来
Don't worry. I can give you a piggyback on our way back
# 你说真的假的
Really?
# 真的 你走不动了我背你回来
Yes. I will give you a piggyback if you are too tired to walk
# 这没有路了哦
There is no road here
# 一砍就是路 开路
Just open a new one
# 这叫逢山开路 遇水架桥
This is "cut paths through the mountains and build bridges across the rivers"
# 别走那么快啊
Don't walk too fast
# 这个野果不好吃耶
This wild fruit is not good to eat
# 不好吃 是不容易吃
They are difficult to eat. Not bad to eat.
# 有没有什么简单一点的
Are there any easy activities for us?
# 不用那个像抓鱼放水爬山路这种
Something that doesn't need us to catch fish, drain a pool, or climb the mountain
# 比如你们家的那个黑猪竹鼠抓出来就可以弄
For example, we can simply catch and "deal with" the black pig and bamboo rat that you keep
# 简单一点的就是去兄弟家玩
An easy activity is to play at my brothers'
# 我的手好像被割了一刀
I guess my hand is cut
# 要小心一点
Be careful
# 没事
It's OK
# 我们下来的时候还走这条路吗
Do we go along this way again when we return?
# 不走这里了
No
# 快到了
We are almost there
# 终于快到了
Arriving at last
# 这些都是啊
All of these are (the wild fruit)
# 我跟你说真的吃多了上厕所上不出来的
Seriously, if you eat too much of this fruit, you will suffer from constipation
# 不骗你的
I am serious
# 上不出来啊
Constipation?
# 全部是籽来的
This fruit is full of seeds
# 把你的肠道给堵住
which will jam your intestines
# 男女都是一样的
no matter you are a man or a woman
# 这个是甜的
This one is sweet
# 这两个黑的 黑的就（是）甜的
These two black ones. The black ones are sweet.
# 哇刚哥 这个我们两个来慢慢享受
Wow. Let's enjoy these
# 终于看到（吃的）东西了
Finally, I can see something to eat
# 往上走这边很多
Come up. There are a lot of fruits here
# 你看这有 这里还有一个
Look. There is another one here
# 你看这三个
Look at these three here
# 吃这个东西最快的速度是这样
The fastest way to eat it is like this
# 把这个屁股摘掉
Remove the butt
# 好累啊吃这个水果
It's so tiring to eat this fruit
# 是啊 要爬山爬那么远
Yep. We need to climb the mountain for quite a while
# 近的地方又没有
There is no such fruit nearby (where we live)
# 我发现你的汗水比我还大（多） 全身都湿透了
I think you are sweating much more than I do. You are totally wet
# 但是多出点汗嘛对身体有好处的
But sweating is somehow good for your health
# 我发现我们为了吃这个野果下了血本
I think we really spent a lot of time and energy on this wild fruit
# 还小的时候我们经常吃这个
We often ate this when we were young
# 太好吃了
It's really delicious
# 看这个山这么高
Look at this mountain. It's so high
# 我和小哥也是全身湿透
This bro and I are also totally wet in our sweat
# 你看这个人身上 头发上都有那个东西（小苍耳）
Look at this guy. She's got that thing (small cocklebur) on her clothes and hair
# 好热啊
It's so hot
# 你又躲在这边吃什么
What are you eating alone here
# 有几个（野果）有点少 我就顺便把它吃了
There are some (wild fruits). Not many. So I just ate them
# 你躲着就要吃饱了
You are getting full while hiding from us
# 来 这个
Come on. Take this one
# 哇 这个大
Wow. This one is big
# 华农说这个吃多了 吃两三斤没问题是吧
Huanong says if you eat too much of this... It's OK to eat 2~3 Jin (1~1.5 kg) at a time, right?
# 吃五六斤拉不出屎来
You will have constipation if you eat 5~6 Jin (2.5~3 kg)
# 那你不是害我啊
Then you are getting me into trouble
# 他吃得比谁都多
He eats more than everyone
# 哦 也是
Hmm. Indeed
# 我的消化系统比较好
I have a strong digestive system
# 对啊 你是（吃）竹鼠、猪都可以
Right. You can eat bamboo rat or pig
# 没问题
No problem
# 我感觉要下雨 #注：这里刚哥的视频中自带的字幕是错的，写成“我们小时候经常吃这个”
I think it's gonna rain
# 你看这个天
Look at the sky
# 乌云密布的
It's dark and cloudy
# 我们是带回去还是吃饱了再回去啊
Do we bring some fruits back? Or we return when we are full?
# 嘿嘿 边走边吃
Haha. Eat while walking
# 边走边吃 我发现你才是边走边吃
Eat while walking. You are the only one who does this
# 我们都没吃饱
None of us is full yet
# 这兄弟耿直 搞了这么多
This bro is so upright. He's got so many
# 所以我很喜欢他啊
So I like him very much
# 经常跟他一起去玩
I often play with him
# 嘿嘿嘿
Hehehe [Laughters]
# 你经常去他们家是吧
You often go to their homes, right?
# 是 串门嘛
Yeah. Just drop by
# 多喝点水 等下很热的
Drink more water. It's gonna be hot soon
# 我一个人能把这吃完
I can eat all these up by myself
# 别动
Stay still
# 都吃出血来了
It's got blood
# 蚊子啊
The mosquito
# 这么高的地方也有蚊子
There are mosquitos at such a high altitude?
# 没事 换一下血才行
It's fine. Sometimes you need to renew your blood
# 那个造血功能啊 造出新血好一点
It's a good exercise for the blood-forming function
# 等下给人家吃完了 人家摘那么多
You are gonna eat them up! They picked so many
# 没事啊 随便吃
Never mind. Help yourself!
# 随便吃 听到没 随便吃
"Help yourself"! You heard that? "Help yourself"!
# 哎呀谢谢
Wow thank you
# 这一下好凉快
It's pretty cool now
# 现在我们是准备下山还是
Are we gonna go down the mountains, or ..?
# 这棵树是去年被雷劈过的 现在死了
This tree was struck by a lightning last year. Now it's dead.
# 它站得太高了 山顶上最高的这棵树
It's too tall. The tallest tree on the top of the mountain.
# 雷为什么会劈它哦
Why did the lightning strike it?
# 为什么会劈它 它站得太高了
Why? Because it is too tall
# 枪都专打出头鸟对吧
The nail that sticks up mostly gets hammered down, right?
# 对
Yep
# 太猖狂了
It's too arrogant
# 犯事犯太多了 不能犯太多事的
It's too haughty. Better to keep the head down
# 你们小心一点 这里扎人得很
Be careful you guys. There are many thorny plants here
# 一定要小心哦
Must be careful
# 拉到树枝来
Hold the branch
# 小心一点 你们这里这个一定要注意安全
Be careful! Pay attention when you pass here
# 这个是不是野柿子哦
Is this wild persimmon？
# 哇 这个是柿子 还没熟
Wow. Indeed. But it's still unripe
# 野柿子 结果没熟 太可惜了
Unripe wild persimmon. What a pity!
# 这个树是扎人的
This tree is thorny
# 现在我们准备下山了
Now we are gonna climb down the mountains
# 但是我们好像走入了这个死胡同里面
But it seems to be a dead end here
# 没事
Don't worry
# 然后你看我们的收获
Look at our harvest
# 就那么一点点
Just a few fruits
# 逢山开路
Cut paths through the mountains
# 把它砍出一条路出来
Just open a new road here
# 慢点哦
Be careful
# 快了快了 坚持就是胜利
Almost there! Persistence is victory!
# 这里野兽走过的路哦
Some beast walked through this path
# 真的是
For sure
# 哪里啊
Where?
# 这里
Here
# 真的是野兽
A beast? Really?
# 你看那个脚印 一脚一个
Look at the footprints. One by one
# 像是什么
What can it be?
# 像野猪
Looks like a boar
# 野猪
A boar?
# 嗯
Yes
# 马上到那个小溪旁了
We are arriving at the creek
# 过了小溪就是大路
After crossing the creek, we will get to the main road
# 小心一点哦
Careful!
# 啊 终于到了
Ahhh! Got here at last
# 这条路出去了就是大路了
Go through this path and we'll see the main road
# 这个水不要去喝哦这个水
Don't drink the water in the creek
# 不要去喝
Don't drink
# 洗脸呢
How about just washing my face?
# 洗脸可以
That's OK
# （你）平时拍的那个摘野果很轻松
It seems really easy to pick the wild fruits in your videos
# 哪有那么容易啊
Not easy at all
# 太难了这个
It's really difficult
# 我们今天爬了一个多小时
We climbed for more than one hour
# 上去爬一个多小时 下来又是
More than one hour to climb up, the same time to get down
# 下来其实更难
Actually, it's even more difficult to climb down
# 下来更难
Indeed
# 对 而且有很多野刺容易搞到手
Yes. And there were a lot of thorny plants that hurt our hands
# 我还好
I'm fine actually
# 我也还好 就稍微轻轻刮了一下
I'm OK as well. Just some scratches
# 轻轻刮了一下 还好有你开路
A tiny scratch. It's great to have you to open the way
# 没事
Don't mention it
# 下一次就是后面的话我们不去爬山了好不好
Next time, I mean, can we not go climbing the mountains?
# 嗯 烧烤哦 烧烤是最简单的
Um? Barbeque then. Barbeque is the simplest
# 对啊
Yes
# 去我家拎两个竹鼠来 去那个场地里面
Just catch two bamboo rats from my farm and take them to that yard
# 我等你这句话等了好久了
I've been waiting for this for a long time
# 那好吧 那我们下一期跟大家分享竹鼠
Alright then. In our next video, we will share with you the bamboo rats
# 好啊
OK
# 一定是你们家抓的哦
You sure they are from your farm?
# 对对对 我去拎我家两只出来
Exactly. I will catch two bamboo rats from my farm
# 我家的比较好吃
The rats in my farm are more delicious
# 拜拜
Bye bye